Hey, English learners, how's it going?
Today, I want to talk about becoming
fluent in English. In this video, I'm
going to talk at normal speed. You have
the subtitles here below, so this will
be good practice for your listening.
There are two definitions of fluency
that I want to go over. So, people think
of fluency in different ways. Some
people think of fluency as just speaking
in a fluid manner, meaning you're
speaking without needing to stop all the
time. You're speaking continuously. It's
just flowing from your mouth, but you
still have a good number of mistakes,
right? That's what many people's
definition of fluency is. However,
there's another definition that some
people
that they support, another definition of
fluency, which is when you're at a very,
very high level, you speak very
accurately. You have just a really,
really, really high level of a language.
Some people think of that as fluency,
right? So, there's
probably no consensus. It's not like,
all right, we can all agree on one
definition of fluency,
but usually people take one of those two
approaches when it comes to fluency.
They think of it in one of those two
ways. Either they're more literal, like,
okay, it's fluid speech that's coming
out of your mouth. There are mistakes,
maybe even a good number of mistakes,
but it's flowing very naturally. Or some
people have a very strict standard, a
very high standard, and I think fluency
refers to just having an extremely high
level in the language, right? Where
you're speaking very, very accurately as
well. So, I'm going to talk about both
of those today. I'm going to talk about
my opinion on how someone reaches those
levels, how someone reaches fluency.
Again, this is my opinion. Other people
will disagree with me. This is just what
I think about this, right? And
ultimately, this type of video is not
just to give you advice or tips or
things like that. It's for your
listening practice. So, whether or not
you agree with me, doesn't really
matter. Uh you're here to practice your
listening and uh just increase and
improve your comprehension. So, uh
that's what we're going to talk about
today. By the way, if you want more
advanced content like this where I speak
at normal speed, make sure to sign up to
become a Listening Time family member.
The link is down below. You can sign up
to become a Listening Time family member
to receive my advanced podcast episodes
in which I speak like this. I speak
fast. Okay? Uh so, uh let's talk about
fluency. Fluency refers to oral
communication, obviously. So, we're
talking about speaking and understanding
here. We're not talking about writing
and reading.
Um that, of course, those things are
important, but here I'm just talking
about your fluency
uh in the oral realm. Okay? So, in order
to be fluent, you need both speaking and
understanding. Okay? A lot of people
just focus on the speaking aspect, but
uh if you can't understand well, I don't
think that people would normally
consider you very fluent if you just
can't understand what people are saying
to you. Right? If you're having every,
you know,
uh 30 seconds or so, you have to say,
"Hey, can you repeat that? Can you
repeat that?" People probably aren't
going to get the feeling that you're
fluent,  , right? So,
you need speaking and understanding. So,
let's talk about a couple different
phases of becoming fluent, whether
that's, you know, reaching the first
definition of fluency or the second that
we went over. So, uh let's talk first
about building a foundation. Okay? Uh
when you're starting out, when you're at
a lower level, you got to build your
foundation for the language, your
foundation of your knowledge of that
language. And in my opinion, that comes
from your comprehension of the language,
your understanding of the language. So,
in this phase, you're going to want to
do tons and tons and tons of listening
practice. This is going to be the main
thing that you do.
Uh of course, some people do like to
speak really early. I'll talk about that
I'll talk about that in just a second.
But let's focus on the main
foundation of your knowledge of a
language, which is what you can
understand, your comprehension, okay?
So once you start to be
once you're able to understand many
things in the language, you're building
up a passive vocabulary, a passive
knowledge of the language, and you can
turn those things into active
knowledge later on, right? But you're
first just building up this foundation
of mostly passive knowledge, but also
active knowledge once you have heard the
same thing many many times, you can
probably just actively say it without
even thinking about it, right? So that's
going to happen, too. But in this phase,
you really want to just focus on
learning as many words as you possibly
can.
Again, first passively, later on they'll
be more active,
but just understanding vocabulary.
That's a really really big key point
here. Using comprehensible input, this
is a term we use to talk about input,
like stuff that you listen to or read,
but in this case we're talking about
oral communication, so listening to
things
that you can understand, but they're a
little challenging for you. So it's not
like you can understand 100% of
everything that's being said, but you
can understand the point of what's being
said, and your brain is trying to kind
of put the puzzle together for the words
that you can't quite understand, but you
get the context. So
using content that isn't way too hard
for you or too easy for you. If you
understand every single thing, every
single word, that's probably too easy
for you, right? You need to use content
that's a little challenging for you, but
that you can still understand generally,
right? That's comprehensible input. That
should be the majority of what you do
when you're building your foundation
to try to become fluent is you need to
listen as much as possible to
comprehensible input. Listen to
a tons and tons of different,
you know, types of audios, videos, you
know, different sources.
Of course, doing reading is also
important as well. It really helps you
learn vocabulary.
And then when you are
like watching videos with subtitles or
listening to something with the
transcript, it's
it's reading too, right? You're
listening and you're reading. So, you're
doing listening and reading practice.
Doing a lot of repetition is really
important when building a foundation,
right? When you're really trying to
just develop a lot better
understanding of a language.
And then even just working on, you know,
speaking well, doing a lot of repetition
is going to help with that because when
you hear the same thing over and over
again, that thing, first it becomes like
your passive knowledge and then you've
heard it so much that you can just
naturally say it as well. You know, it
becomes an active vocabulary word or
phrase that you know, right? So, doing a
lot of repetition both like direct
repetition where you're just listening
to the same thing again and again. And
then also like indirect repetition like
maybe you're listening to
like one YouTuber or something like
that. You just listen to all their
videos about one topic. So, it's not
literal repetition where you're just
listening to the same video over and
over again, but you're hearing them talk
over and over again about the same
topic. And of course, we tend to use the
same types of phrases and words. We have
a certain style of speaking. So, you're
going to get repetition just listening
to the same person talking about the
same topic, right? So, that type of
repetition and then explicit direct
repetition where you're just listening
to the same thing over and over again.
Both of those are really really powerful
tools, powerful methods to help you
build your foundation.
And so, after you do hundreds of hours
of this, of just really intense
listening repetition, just learning
vocabulary and all this, you're going to
eventually reach a level where you can
understand one person when they're
speaking to you, or you can understand a
person that you're listening to on
YouTube or something like that. And then
you're going to develop a very
wide range of passive words, like
words that you know passively. Meaning
like when you hear them, you know them.
You can understand what the person is
saying, right? You will eventually know
most of the words that you hear. If you
do this for hundreds of hours, you'll
reach the level where most of the things
that someone says to you, you will be
able to understand, right? And that's a
great feeling, okay? An optional part of
this first phase of your learning is
speaking. And I say it's optional
because some people don't like to speak
early, and that's okay, right?
Like I think in general I'm someone that
doesn't really like to speak that early,
but I know other people that really like
speaking early. And it can work for
them, or maybe it can work for you to
not speak early. I've talked to many
people who did not speak early, and then
finally they have a conversation with me
and it's their first conversation that
they've ever had with a native speaker,
and they're speaking great. We're having
a full-on conversation, even though it's
the first time they've ever spoken to
someone. So, you can reach a pretty good
level where you can start to speak to
people even without doing a lot of
speaking practice in this early phase,
okay? So, that's why I say that this is
optional. Some people really really like
to do this though, so, you know, it's
obviously just your choice.
The next phase though, after you've
built this foundation, where you can
actually understand a person pretty
well, like you can understand the
majority of the things that they say to
you. You can already interact in the
language like that.
Once you're at that intermediate level,
then things change a little bit because
well, let's just first talk about where
you're at at this level. Once you're you
know, I think all of you if you just do
this, you're all going to reach the
level where you can understand someone
even when they're speaking at normal
speed. You can understand them pretty
well. Um you guys can all reach that
level. Okay, you guys all have that
ability just from doing tons and tons of
listening practice repetition
using comprehensible input reading, you
know, you're going to reach this level.
Okay? However, there still will be gaps
in your comprehension at this level.
It's not like you're going to understand
every single thing that someone says and
different speaking styles can be hard
and you might even have major
difficulties when it comes to group
settings like when you're listening to
more than one person speaking, right?
That's something that I dealt with when
I was learning Spanish. Like I was able
to talk one-on-one to someone really
well, but then if you threw me into a
group setting, suddenly I was like
like there was so many things I couldn't
understand, right? So even at an
intermediate level, you might still have
those gaps. It might still be hard for
you in a group setting, right? So at
this level
there's a few things that you'll be able
to do to increase your comprehension.
You need to start spending more time
listening to more than one person
speaking, right? It's still good to
listen to one person speaking. That's
still great, but adding in content where
you're listening to more than one person
speaking is essential, right? By the
way, that's why I make my US
conversations podcast. I talk to
different English teachers from around
the country and I transcribe our
conversation. We speak at normal speed.
It's authentic. So it's good practice
for that specific type of practice. If
you want that, the link is down below as
well. But you have to start practicing
with that.
Um you know, because if you cannot
function in a group setting, people are
not going to consider you fluent, right?
If you talk pretty well one-on-one, but,
you know, suddenly you're in the car
with two or three people and you can't
follow the conversation, you know,
people aren't going to consider you
fluent, right? Even if you speak fairly
well. Okay? So, being able to understand
people in different settings, different
group settings this is an essential
when it comes to fluency, right?
Uh so, uh you need to be able to to
interact in group settings, be able to
understand more than more than one
person is speaking.
Um you're also, when it comes to the
actual like you speaking,
uh it's going to be really important for
you to actually integrate a lot of
speaking practice into your routine now.
Now, it's not so optional, right? If you
actually want to reach a level of
fluency, yeah, in the first phase when
you're, you know, just trying to build
that foundation, it's it's optional,
right? In my opinion, okay? Once you're
at this intermediate level, once you can
understand people, you know, well, then
speaking becomes a priority and becomes
a big priority, okay? And I'm sure, you
know, those of you watching right now,
this is what you're most interested in
probably. You want to be able to speak
fluidly, speak naturally, right? Well,
how do we do this?
Well, when we speak naturally, when we
speak fluidly, when we say things in a
natural way without needing to stop and
think and, you know, put put the
sentence together in our brain, it's
because we're saying things that we
already know are correct, okay? Because
we've heard them millions of times. I'm
exaggerating here, but we've heard them
many, many times, okay? So, that's why
listening and repetition is so powerful
to help your speaking. Because once
you've heard someone say a certain
phrase like 200 times, you just know
that it's that it's correct and you just
say it naturally, right? It can just
come out of your mouth without you
realizing it. That's happened to me many
times in different languages where I
just randomly say something and it's
like the first time I've said it and I'm
like, "Whoa, I've never said that
before, but it's just so natural to say
it because I've heard it so many times.
I know it's correct, right? It is just
natural for me to say that." So, that's
kind of what we want to do in order to
become fluent. So, you got to continue
doing tons and tons and tons and tons of
listening practice, okay? Reading as
well, but especially listening practice
as we're talking about oral
communication here, right? You know, for
me, for like French, when I started
speaking French regularly, I had already
done hundreds, thousands maybe, of hours
of intense,
uh, just listening,
you know, where I wasn't just listening
to like content made for French
learners. Like, I was listening to
native content, right? You know, YouTube
channels of, uh, online entrepreneurs
talking about, you know, online
entrepreneurship and they're just
talking to other French speakers. Like,
I was using that content before I even,
you know, was having conversations in
French. I was listening to native
content just every day, just, you know,
doing this just so much of this and
doing repetition and, you know, all of
this just gave me so many phrases, so
many words and phrases that I could
already just say naturally without even
thinking about them. So, when I had my
first, like, when I first started having
regular conversations in French, I could
already say so many things naturally
just because of all that, you know,
listening I had done, right? And of
course, I had to start filling in my
gaps, but I already had just this great,
great foundation. So, listening is just,
you know, that's the pillar. That's the
the foundation of your knowledge in a
language, okay? What you can understand,
your understanding in that language,
right?
So,
it can be discouraging when you're at
the intermediate phase because you know
a lot of words, whether it's passively
or actively. And even just passively,
you know so many words. You know so many
of the common words. You know like most
of the common words. And so, the things
that you don't know at this phase are
things that don't come up that often,
right? So,
um things that
uh come up really often, you've already
learned those things in your foundation
phase, when you're just like building
your foundation. But then, you know,
once you reach a higher level, you're at
an intermediate level, the things that
you don't know, you don't hear them that
often because they're not as common. And
so, it can feel like you're not really
learning a lot of new things because it
takes so long for you to hear those same
words again and again and get that
necessary repetition, right? And so, one
thing you can do is you start to try to
actively fill in your own gaps just in
an active way, where you speak and you
see what you can't actually say yet, and
then you, you know, write down those
things, you translate them, and then you
fill in those gaps, and you search for
your own gaps instead of just waiting
for your gaps to get filled through your
own listening practice. You know, speak.
Speak to someone or speak to yourself,
and actively fill in those gaps, right?
So, you're going to need to do this if
you want to really increase your your
your level of speaking
in a faster way. Obviously, just doing a
bunch of listening is going to help your
speaking, but if you want to speed this
up if you speed this up if you want to
get, you know, reach a higher level in a
shorter amount of time, it's great to
actively do this. And so,
you know, what I did, I haven't done as
much recently, but what I was doing a
lot last year was I was speaking to
myself in French, usually out loud.
And I would do this like almost every
day. And when you do this almost every
day, you just keep on finding more and
more gaps, you those gaps, you learn the
things that you're trying to say but you
can't say, you know, you actively do
this, you're going to
you know, really increase, improve your
your level of speaking, right? So, do
this, do it frequently, speak to other
people, you know, use uh these different
tools and websites where you can take
classes with native speakers, do that
and also speak to yourself, right? Um
you know, just speaking whether it's to
yourself or to another person, you do
this frequently, you're going to train
those speaking muscles, your ability to
just say things that you know, and then
you're also just going to find your gaps
and you want to actively do that, right?
And the way we get better is we find
what we don't know and then we learn it,
right? That's how we close our gaps,
that's how we get better at speaking.
And so,
uh you know, it's pretty basic,
everything I'm saying right here in
terms of like the philosophy behind it,
right? Um you're you're doing tons of
listening, you're doing a ton of
repetition, but you're also at this
phase, you're actively trying to
increase your speaking, to improve your
speaking by filling in your gaps, right?
And so, those two things, if you do them
for, you know, many, many hours, you're
going to reach a level where you're at
that first level of fluent, that first
definition of fluency that we talked
about, where you can
speak pretty naturally with mistakes cuz
you're still filling in your gaps, it's
still going to take a while, but you're
speaking naturally, you can interact
with people, you can even interact with
people in a group setting, right? That's
a really, really, really great level in
a language. Once you can reach Once
you've reached that level, it's like
people just view you as like you're good
in that language, right? And for many
people, that's fluency right there.
Well, you might tell me, "Well, I want
to reach that second definition of
fluency where I'm just really, really
good and I'm not making a lot of
mistakes and I'm just like speaking
extremely well. Well, how do you reach
that level? Well, you do this, but you
do it more intensively or
and/or you do it for many, many, many,
many more hours. Okay? Add hundreds, if
not thousands, of more hours of what I
just said right now, and you can
eventually reach that second definition
of fluency, depending on which
definition you're going for, right? But
there's not like another secret key to
reach that other level. It's just that
if you want to be more accurate in your
fluid speech, you got to have more
phrases that are just in your mind that
you just know without even thinking
about. You just know they're correct and
you just say them, right? That's how we
as native speakers talk. So, if you want
to have that as well, you know, imagine
how much listening you need to do, how
much repetition you need to do, how much
speaking you need to do where you're
filling in your gaps. And then, not only
that, is something I I forgot to
mention, not only filling in your gaps,
but actively learning vocabulary as
well. Like, you know, it's one thing to
just say, "Okay, I didn't know how to
say this. Let me translate it. All
right, that's how you say it." Another
thing, a better way than just doing
that, is to now try to actively learn
that phrase, learn that word that you
didn't know, right? And that could be
with flash cards or maybe you have some
other way. I've done flash cards and
it's worked for me, but actively trying
to learn words and phrases that you
need. You don't need every word. You
don't need every phrase. You just need
the words and phrases that you use,
okay? And, you know, this is just a
process that takes a lot, a lot of time.
Okay? People, you know, constantly, you
know, tell me that they have a problem.
They have this problem. They have this
problem because they're not speaking
accurately. It's not natural for them.
They're They They freeze up when they're
speaking. Well, that's not a problem.
That's what the process is. You have to
get through that by doing much more
listening, much more repetition, much
more speaking practice, filling in your
gaps, and actively learning vocabulary.
It really is simple when you think of
that, you know, whole philosophy behind
it. So, these are just my opinions, uh
of course, and some people might
disagree with me, but I think it's
pretty basic at the end of the day. The
big thing is that it takes a ton of
time, and uh it takes active practice as
well, right? If you're doing all this
just very passively, you're not really
invested in this, it's not going to be
the same thing. If you're actively doing
this, if you're actively engaged, if you
really are just like there in it doing
this, you know, doing it in a very
active way, you know, eventually you're
going to reach your goals. It's just
that if you have that second definition
of fluency, it's going to take a long
time, okay? A really long time. Or it
could be a shorter amount of time, but
you're going to be spending many, many
hours just every week doing this, and
most people don't have that time. So,
you could shorten it, it might not be
that long in terms of like years, but
you're going to have to do tons and tons
of practice. And I'm not trying to
discourage you, I'm just trying to make
it clearer why you're not at that level
of fluency, whatever definition you
have. It's you know, it's a matter of
time, being engaged with it, and it
being active, actively trying to fill in
your gaps, actively trying to understand
in group settings, you know, doing this
practice actively, okay?
My thoughts were a little scattered
today, but I think you guys got my
point. Uh you can let me know down in
the comments what you think about this,
or if you have any other ideas. Uh
remember to check out my uh US
Conversations Podcast, so you can try
listening to uh more than one person
talking. This is a skill that you need
to develop, as we just talked about. So,
if you want that, that link is down
below, so go down and click on that. And
if you just want more advanced content
like this, where I'm speaking at normal
speed, make sure to become a Listening
Time Family Member, and so you'll get my
advanced podcast episodes. That link is
also down below. All right, thank you
all for listening, for watching this
video, and I'll talk to you in the next
one.